# Yohan Chatelain

Montreal, Quebec | (514) 206-2468

yohan.chatelain@gmail.com

# Summary

I am a postdoctoral fellow at the University of Concordia Montreal. My research activities include computer arithmetic, numerical analysis, floating-point optimizations, and High-Performance Computing. I am currently focusing on neuroimaging pipelines to characterize numerical stability and improve performance.

# Experience

#### Postdoctoral Fellowship | Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal

09/2020 - Present

Big Data Infrastructures for Neuroinformatics - Gina Cody School of Engineering and Computer Science

**Goal**: Studying numerical instabilities in neuroimaging pipelines Projects involved:

• LivingPark, to improve the generalizability and robustness of MRI-derived biomarkers of Parkinson's Disease (project)

• InterFLOP project aims at providing a modular and scalable platform to analyze floating-point arithmetic (project)

• ReproVIP aims at evaluating and improve the reproducibility of scientific results in the field of medical imaging (project)

• Non-regression tests for MRI preprocessing, statistical tests using numerical uncertainties to quantify acceptable variation bounds

• Numerical stability evaluation of human brain tractometry within PyAFQ, AccelNet IN-BIC funding (project)

• Pytracer, a trace-based Python tool for visualizing numerical instabilities of Python codes (project / paper)

• Fuzzy, an ecosystem for evaluating the effect of numerical errors on computational tools (project / paper)

• Significantdigit, Python package for solid statistical analysis of stochastic arithmetic (project)

### Ph.D. student | UVSQ | France, Île-de-France, Versailles

10/2016 - 12/2019

Li-Parad - Université de Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines (UVSQ)

**Goal**: Develop tools for debugging and optimizing floating-point computations in HPC Projects involved:

• Veritracer, a tool for visualizing numerical instabilities over time (project / paper)

• VPREC, a verificarlo's backend to simulate reduced floating-point precision (paper)

• Verificarlo is a tool for debugging and assessing floating point precision and reproducibility. (project)

### Software Engineer Intern | Intel Corporation | USA, Oregon, Hillsboro

01/2019 - 07/2019

Numerics US team - Intel Jones Farm

Goal: Development of optimized mathematic libraries (Numerics US team)

- Contribution to the development of elementary mathematical functions (libm)
- $\bullet$  Code modernization (half of the library's function) to ensure quality standards
- Setting up continuous integration for validation tests suite with internal tools

### Software Developer Intern | UVSQ | France, Île-de-France, Versailles

04/2016 - 09/2016

Li-Parad - Université de Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines (UVSQ)

**Goal**: Internship for Master's degree validation

Projects involved:

- CERE, Code Extractor and REplayer (project / paper)
- Construction of an energetic prediction model in the HPC context

### Software Developer Intern | ECR (CEA, Intel, UVSQ) | France, Île-de-France, Bruyères-le-Châtel

05/2015 - 09/2015

Exascale Computing Research

(Commissariat a l'Energie Atomique, Intel and Université de Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines joined laboratory)

**Goal**: C codes piecewise specialization based on value profiling

- Implementation of an automatic functions specializer in LLVM
- Implementation of a value profiling method in
- Characterization of speedups gained with specialization

### Software Developer Intern | LRI | France, Île-de-France, Saclay

05/2015 - 09/2015

Laboratoire de Recherche en Informatique - Université Paris-Sud XI and CNRS

Goal: Implementation of program termination criterion for a generic first-order call-by-value language in ML style in

# Education

# Ph.D. Université Paris-Saclay | Versailles, Île-de-France

12/2019

Supervisors: William JALBY, Pablo DE OLIVEIRA CASTRO

Title: "Tools for debugging and optimizing floating-point computations in HPC"

Field: Computer sciences

### Master Université de Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines | Versailles, Île-de-France

09/2016

Université de Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines (UVSQ) member of Université Paris-Saclay

Field: High-Performance Computing

## Bachelor Université Paris-Sud XI | Orsay, Île-de-France

06/2014

Université Paris-Sud XI (UPSud) replaced by Université Paris-Saclay Field: Computer sciences

# **Teaching**

# Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal

Fundamentals of programming | Bachelor level | Course Instructor

Fall 2023

Introductory course to the basic principles of programming with classes and objects using C++

## UVSQ | France, Île-de-France, Versailles

Université de Versailles Saint Quentin-en-Yvelines (UVSQ)

Compilers | Bachelor level | 72h

2018-2019

Overview of compilation from language parsing to assembly generation with practical implementation in LLVM

Advanced Algorithms | Bachelor level | 72h

2016-2018

Time and space complexity, recursive schemes and graph traversal

Parallel Architectures | Master level | 40h

2016-2018

Shared and distributed memory parallelization, cache policy, network topology and analysis of research publications

# Mentoring

### Ph.D. level

Ines GONZALES PEPE | Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal

09/2023 - present

- o Subject: "Numerical stability of deep learning in bioinformatics"
- o Supervisor: Tristan GLATARD | Mentoring: Gregory KIAR (50%)

Ali SALARI | Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal

10/2020 - 02/2022

- o Subject: "The effect of Computational Environments on Big Data Processing Pipelines in Neuroimaging"
- o Supervisor: Tristan GLATARD | Mentoring: Gregory KIAR (50%)

#### Master level

Ines GONZALES PEPE | Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal

09/2021 - 09/2023

- Subject: "Numerical stability of DeepGoPlus infererence" (preprint paper)
- o Co-supervisor: Tristan GLATARD (50%)

Damien THENOT | UVSQ | France, Versailles |

06/2018 - 09/2018

- o Subject: "Development of a Java IDE for Veritracer"
- o Co-supervisor: Pablo DE OLIVEIRA CASTRO (50%)

## **Undergraduate level**

Nigel YONG | Concordia University | Canada, Quebec, Montreal

05/2021 - 06/2021

- o Subject: "Optimizing performance of PyTracer"
- o Co-supervisor: Tristan GLATARD (50%)

- o Subject: "Reducing numerical precision preserves classification accuracy in Mondrian Forests" (published paper)
- o Co-supervisors: Martin KHANNOUZ (33%) | Tristan GLATARD (33%)

### Grants

**AccelNet IN-BIC** 10/2021 \$10,000 (USD)

PI: Yohan Chatelain Understanding the magnitude, origins, and implications of numerical instabilities for human brain tractometry within PyAFQ

Concordia Horizon Post-doctoral Fellowship PI: Yohan Chatelain

Studying numerical instabilities in neuroimaging

2020-2022 \$50,000/yr. (USD)

# Research

### Peer-reviewed publications in journals

1. PyTracer: Automatically profiling numerical instabilities in Python

Yohan Chatelain, Nigel Yong, Gregory Kiar, Tristan Glatard. IEEE Transactions on Computers (IEEE TC) (2022)

- 2. Data Augmentation Through Monte Carlo Arithmetic Leads to More Generalizable Classification in Connectomics Gregory Kiar, Yohan Chatelain, Ali Salari, Alan C. Evans, Tristan Glatard In Neurons, Behavior, Data Analysis and Theory, 2021.
- 3. Numerical Uncertainty in Analytical Pipelines Lead to Impactful Variability in Brain Networks Gregory Kiar, Yohan Chatelain, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Eric Petit, Ariel Rokem, Gaël Varoquaux, Bratislav Misic, Alan C. Evans, Tristan Glatard. In PLOS ONE (2021).
- 4. Piecewise holistic autotuning of parallel programs with CERE Mihail Popov, Chadi Akel, Yohan Chatelain, William Jalby, and Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, vol. 29, Aug 2017.

### Peer-reviewed publications in conferences

- 1. Numerical Uncertainty of Convolutional Neural Networks Inference for Structural Brain MRI Analysis. Inés Gonzalez Pepe, Vinuyan Sivakolunthu, Hae Lang Park, Yohan Chatelain, Tristan Glatard. Uncertainty for Safe Utilization of Machine Learning in Medical Imaging (UNSURE, MICCAI) (2023)
- 2. Reproducibility of tumor segmentation outcomes with a deep learning model Morgane Des Ligneris, Axel Bonnet, Yohan Chatelain, Tristan Glatard, Michaël Sdika, Gaël Vila, Valentine Wargnier-Dauchelle, Sorina Pop, Carole Frindel. International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging (ISBI), 2023.
- 3. Reducing numerical precision preserves classification accuracy in Mondrian Forests Marc Vicuna, Martin Khannouz, Gregory Kiar, Yohan Chatelain, Tristan Glatard. 6th Workshop on Real-time Stream Analytics, Stream Mining, CER/CEP & Stream Data Management In 2021 IEEE International Conference on Big Data (Big Data) (pp. 2785-2790).
- 4. Accurate simulation of operating system updates in neuroimaging using Monte-Carlo arithmetic Ali Salari, Yohan Chatelain, Gregory Kiar, Tristan Glatard.
- Uncertainty for Safe Utilization of Machine Learning in Medical Imaging (UNSURE, MICCAI) (2021) pp. 14-23. Springer Publishing.
- 5. Automatic exploration of reduced floating-point representations in iterative methods Yohan Chatelain, Eric Petit, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Ghislain Lartigue, David Defour (2019, August).

In the European Conference on Parallel Processing (Euro-Par) (pp. 481-494). Springer, Cham.

6. VeriTracer: Context-enriched tracer for floating-point arithmetic analysis

Yohan Chatelain, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, Eric Petit, David Defour, Jordan Bieder, and Marc Torrent. In 2018 IEEE 25th Symposium on Computer Arithmetic (ARITH) (pp. 61-68). IEEE

### **Preprints**

- 1. A numerical variability approach to results stability tests and its application to neuroimaging Yohan Chatelain, Loïc Tetrel, Christopher J Markiewicz, Mathias Goncalves, Gregory Kiar, Oscar Esteban, Pierre Bellec, Tristan Glatard. arXiv:2307.01373
- 2. Longitudinal brain structure changes in Parkinson's disease: a replication study Andrzej Sokolowski, Nikhil Bhagwat, Yohan Chatelain, Mathieu Dugre, Alexandru Hanganu, Oury Monchi, Brent McPherson, Michelle Wang, Jean-Baptiste Poline, Madeleine Sharp, Tristan Glatard. bioRxiv:2023.04.28.538743

- 3. Predicting Parkinson's disease progression using MRI-based white matter radiomic biomarker and machine learning: a reproducibility and replicability study
  - Mohanad Arafe, Nikhil Bhagwat, **Yohan Chatelain**, Mathieu Dugre, Andrzej Sokolowski, Michelle Wang, Yiming Xiao, Madeleine Sharp, Jean-Baptiste Poline, Tristan Glatard. bioRxiv:2023.05.05.539590.
- 4. Numerical Stability of DeepGOPlus Inference
  Ines Gonzalez Pepe, **Yohan Chatelain**, Gregory Kiar, Tristan Glatard. arXiv preprint arXiv:2212.06361.

## **Communications at international conferences (summary)**

- 1. Testing the long-term reproducibility of fMRIPrep results
  - **Yohan Chatelain**, Loïc Tetrel, Christopher J. Markiewicz, Gregory Kiar, Oscar Esteban, Pierre Bellec and Tristan Glatard. OHBM 2022, Glasgow, Scotland.
- 2. Fuzzy environments for the perturbation, evaluation, and application of numerical uncertainty via MCA in the scientific Python ecosystem
  - Gregory Kiar, Yohan Chatelain, Ali Salari, Eric Petit, Pablo de Oliveira Castro, and Tristan Glatard. SciPy Conference, 2021.
- 3. Towards Abinit on ExaScale supercomputers: the challenge for electronic structure physicists
  Jordan Bieder, Marc Torrent, and **Yohan Chatelain**. APS Meeting Abstracts. 2018

### **Communications at international conferences (summary)**

- 1. IXPUG 2019: Intel Extreme Performance Users Group, CERN, Geneva, Switzerland
- 2.IXPUG 2018: Intel Extreme Performance Users Group, Intel Corporation, Hillsboro, OR, USA
- 3. ESTN 2018: 8èmes École Thématique de Simulation Numérique, Cargèse, 2018
- 4. RAIM 2017: 9èmes Rencontres «Arithmétique de l'Informatique Mathématique», Lyon, 2017
- 5. ABIDEV 2017: The 8th ABINIT developer's workshop, Frejus, 2017